1 Text Access  
 
ChengXiang  “Cheng” Zhai  
Department of Computer Science  
University of Illinois at Urbana -Champaign  
Course Schedule  
2 Big Text Data  Small Relevant Data  
  Search Engine  Recommender  
System  2. Text Access  11. Recommendation  3. Text Retrieval Problem  
10. Web Search  User  
1. Natural Language Content Analysis  4. Text Retrieval Methods  
7. Evaluation  6. System  
Implementation  5. Vector Space Model  
8. Probabilistic Model  
9. Feedback   2. Text Access  
Access to Relevant Text Data  
How can a text information system help users 
get access to the relevant text data?  
 
•Push vs. Pull  
•Querying vs. Browsing  
3 
Two Modes of Text Access: Pull vs. Push  
•Pull Mode ( search engines ) 
–Users take initiative  
–Ad hoc information need  
•Push  Mode ( recommender systems ) 
–Systems take initiative  
–Stable information need or system has good 
knowledge about a user’s need  
 4 
Pull Mode: Querying vs. Browsing  
•Querying  
–User enters a (keyword) query  
–System returns relevant documents  
–Works well when the user knows what keywords to use  
•Browsing  
–User navigates into relevant information by following a path 
enabled by the structures on the documents  
–Works well when the user wants to explore information, doesn’t 
know what keywords to use, or can’t conveniently enter a query  
5 
Information Seeking as Sightseeing  
•Sightseeing: Know address of an attraction?  
–Yes: take a taxi and go directly to the site  
–No: walk around or take a taxi to a nearby place then walk  
•Information seeking: Know exactly what you want to 
find?  
–Yes: use the right keywords as a query and find the 
information directly  
–No: browse the information space or start with a rough 
query and then browse  
 
6 
Summary  
7 Big Text Data  Small Relevant Data  
  Search Engine  Recommender  
System  2. Text Access  User  
1. Natural Language Content Analysis  Querying  
+ 
Browsing  + Push  Pull 
Additional Reading  
N. J. Belkin  and W. B. Croft. 1992. Information 
filtering and information retrieval: two sides of the 
same coin?. Commun . ACM  35, 12 (Dec. 1992), 29 -
38. 
8 
