Opinion Mining and Sentiment Analysis:  
Latent Aspect Rating Analysis (Part 2)  
 
ChengXiang “Cheng” Zhai  
Department of Computer Science  
University of Illinois at Urbana -Champaign  
1 
A Unified Generative Model for LARA [Wang et al. 11]  
Aspects  
location  
amazing  
walk  
anywhere  
terrible  
front -desk  
smile  
unhelpful  room  
dirty  
appointed  
smelly  Location  
Room  
Service  Aspect Rating  
Any Entity  
2 Excellent location in walking 
distance to Tiananmen Square and 
shopping streets . That’s the best 
part of this hotel! 
The rooms are 
getting really old . Bathroom was 
nasty. The fixtures were falling off, 
lots of cracks and everything 
looked dirty . I don’t think it worth 
the price. 
Service was the most 
disappointing part, especially the 
door men. this is not how you treat 
guests, this is not hospitality.  
Review  
Topic Model  Aspect Weight  
0.86  
0.04  
0.10  
Hotel  Value  Room  Location  Cleanliness  
HOTEL  1 4.2(4.7)  3.8(3.1)  4.0(4.2)  4.1(4.2)  
HOTEL  2 4.3(4.0)  3.9(3.3)  3.7(3.1)  4.2(4.7)  
HOTEL  3 3.7(3.8)  4.4(3.8)  4.1(4.9)  4.5(4.8)  Sample Result 1: Rating Decomposition [Wang et al. 10]  
•Hotels with the same overall rating but different aspect ratings  
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
•Reveal detailed opinions at the aspect level  
3 (All 5 Stars hotels, ground -truth in parenthesis)  
Sample Result 2: Comparison of Reviewers 
[Wang et al. 10]  
•Per-Reviewer Analysis  
–Different reviewers’ ratings on the same hotel  
 
 
 
 
 
–Reveal differences in opinions of different reviewers  
4 Reviewer  Value  Room  Location  Cleanliness  
Reviewer  1 3.7(4.0)  3.5(4.0)  3.7(4.0)  5.8(5.0)  
Reviewer  2 5.0(5.0)  3.0(3.0)  5.0(4.0)  3.5(4.0)  
Sample Result 3: Aspect -Specific Sentiment Lexicon  
[Wang et al. 10]  
5 Value  Rooms  Location  Cleanliness  
resort  22.80  view  28.05  restaurant  24.47  clean  55.35  
 value  19.64  comfortable  23.15  walk  18.89  smell  14.38  
excellent  19.54  modern  15.82  bus  14.32  linen  14.25  
worth  19.20  quiet  15.37  beach  14.11  maintain  13.51  
bad  -24.09  carpet  -9.88  wall  -11.70  smelly  -0.53  
money  -11.02  smell  -8.83  bad  -5.40  urine  -0.43  
terrible  -10.01  dirty  -7.85  road  -2.90  filthy  -0.42  
overprice  -9.06  stain   -5.85  website  -1.67  dingy  -0.38  
Learn sentimental information directly from the data.  
Sample Result 4: Validating Preference Weights 
[Wang et al. 10]  
6 City Avg. Price  Group  Val/Loc  Val/ Rm Val/Ser  
Amsterdam  241.6  top-10 190.7  214.9  221.1  
bot-10 270.8  333.9  236.2  
San 
Francisco  261.3  top-10 214.5  249.0  225.3  
bot-10 321.1  311.1  311.4  
Florence  272.1  top-10 269.4  248.9  220.3  
bot-10 298.9  293.4  292.6  Top-10: Reviewers with the highest Val/X ratio (emphasize “value”)  
Bot-10: Reviewers with the lowest Val/X ratio (emphasize a non -value aspect)  
Higher!  
Application 1: Rated Aspect Summarization  
7 Aspect  Summary  Rating  
Value  Truly unique character and a great location at a reasonable price Hotel Max 
was an excellent choice for our recent three night stay in Seattle.  3.1 
Overall not a negative experience; however, considering that the hotel 
industry is very much in the impressing business, there was a lot of room 
for improvement.  1.7 
Location  The location, a short walk to downtown and Pike Place market, made  the 
hotel a good choice.  3.7 
When you visit a big metropolitan city, be prepared to hear a little traffic 
outside!  1.2 
Business 
Service  You can pay for wireless by the day or use the complimentary Internet in 
the business center behind the lobby, though.  2.7 
My only complaint is the daily charge for Internet access when you can 
pretty much connect to wireless on the streets anymore.  0.9 
Application 2: Discover Consumer Preferences  
 [Wang et al. 2011]  
•Amazon reviews: No guidance  
 
8 battery life  accessory  service  file format  volume  video  
Application 3: User Rating Behavior Analysis  
[Wang et al. 10]  
 
9 Expensive Hotel  Cheap Hotel  
5 Stars  3 Stars  5 Stars  1 Star  
Value  0.134  0.148  0.171  0.093  
Room  0.098  0.162  0.126  0.121  
Location  0.171  0.074  0.161  0.082  
Cleanliness  0.081  0.163  0.116  0.294  
Service  0.251  0.101  0.101  0.049  
People  like  expensive hotels  
because of  good service.  People  like cheap hotels 
because of good value.  
Application 4: Personalized Ranking of Entities  
[Wang et al. 10]  
Query: 0.9 value  
             0.1 others  
Non -personalized  
Personalized  
 
(Query -specific)  
10 
Summary of Opinion Mining  
•Very important with a lot of applications!  
•Sentiment analysis can be done using text categorization 
techniques  
–With enriched feature representation  
–With consideration of ordering of the categories  
•Generative models are powerful for mining latent user 
preferences  
•Most approaches were proposed for product reviews  
•Opinion mining from news and social media remains 
challenging  
11 
Suggested Reading  
•Bing Liu, Sentiment analysis and opinion mining , Morgan & Claypool 
Publishers, 2012.   
•Bo Pang and Lillian Lee, Opinion mining and sentiment analysis, Foundations 
and Trends in Information Retrieval  2(1-2), pp. 1 –135, 2008.  
•Hongning Wang, Yue Lu, and ChengXiang  Zhai , Latent aspect rating analysis 
on review text data: a rating regression approach. In Proceedings of ACM 
KDD 2010, pp. 783 -792, 2010.  DOI=10.1145/1835804.1835903  
•Hongning Wang, Yue Lu, and ChengXiang  Zhai . 2011. Latent aspect rating 
analysis without aspect keyword supervision. In Proceedings of ACM KDD 
2011 , pp. 618-626. DOI=10.1145/2020408.2020505  
12 
