Text Categorization: Motivation  
 
ChengXiang “Cheng” Zhai  
Department of Computer Science  
University of Illinois at Urbana- Champaign  
1 
Text Categorization 
2 Real World 
 Observed World Text Data  
(English)  Perceive Express  
(Perspective)  3. Topic mining & analysis  
4. Opinion mining and  
    sentiment analysis  5. Text -based prediction 
1.Natural language 
processing  & text representation  3. Topic mining and analysis  5. Text -based prediction 
1.Natural language processing and text representation  
2. Word association mining and analysis  
Overview 
•What is text categorization?  
•Why text categorization?  
•How to do text categorization?  
–Generative probabilistic models  
–Discriminative approaches  
•How to evaluate categorization results?  
 
3 This lecture  
4 Text Categorization 
•Given the following:  
–A set of predefined categories , possibly forming a hierarchy  
   and often  
–A training set of labeled text objects  
•Task: Classify  a text object into one or more of the categories   
Categorization  
System  
… Sports  
Business 
 Education  
 Science  
 
 … Sports  
Business 
Education  Text Objects  
Training data  
(known categories)  Categorization Results  
5 Examples of Text Categorization 
•Text objects can vary (e.g., documents, passages, or collections of text)  
•Categories can also vary  
–“Internal” categories that characterize a text object (e.g., topical categories, 
sentiment categories)  
–“External” categories that characterize an entity associated with the text object (e.g., 
author attribution or any other meaningful categories associated with text data)  
•Some examples of applications  
–News categorization, literature article categorization (e.g., MeSH  annotations)  
–Spam email detection/filtering  
–Sentiment categorization of product reviews or tweets  
–Automatic email sorting/routing   
–Author attribution  
6 Variants of Problem Formulation 
•Binary categorization: Only two categories  
–Retrieval: {relevant -doc, non -relevant -doc} 
–Spam filtering: {spam, non-spam}  
–Opinion: {positive, negative} 
•K-category  categorization: More than two categories  
–Topic categorization: {sports, science, travel, business,…} 
–Email routing: {folder1, folder2, folder3,…}  
•Hierarchical categorization: Categories form a hierarchy  
•Joint categorization: Multiple related  categorization tasks done 
in a joint manner  
Binary categorization can potentially support all other categorizations  
7 Why Text Categorization?  
•To enrich text representation  (more understanding of text)  
–Text can now be represented in multiple levels (keywords + categories)  
–Semantic categories assigned can be directly or indirectly useful for an 
application  
–Semantic categories facilitate aggregation of text content (e.g., aggregating all positive/negative opinions about a product) 
•To infer properties of entities associated with text data 
(discovery of knowledge about the world ) 
–As long as an entity can be associated with text data, we can always use the text data to help categorize the associated entities  
–E.g., discovery of non -native speakers of a language;  prediction of 
party affiliation based on a political speech  
 
