Text Representation  
 
ChengXiang  “Cheng” Zhai  
Department of Computer Science  
University of Illinois at Urbana -Champaign  
1 
Text Representation  
2 Real World  
 Observed World  Text Data  
(English)  Perceive  Express  
2. Word association 
mining  & analysis  (Perspective)  3. Topic mining & analysis  
4. Opinion mining &  
    sentiment analysis  5. Text -based prediction  
1.Natural language 
processing  & text 
representation  3. Topic mining & analysis  5. Text -based prediction  
1.Natural language 
processing  & text 
representation  
A   dog   is   chasing   a   boy   on   the   playground  String of characters  
3 Sequence of words  A   dog   is   chasing   a   boy   on   the   playground  
Det Noun  Aux Verb  Det Noun  Prep  Det Noun  + POS tags  
+ Syntactic structures  Noun Phrase  Complex Verb  Noun Phrase  Noun Phrase  
Prep Phrase  Verb Phrase  
Verb Phrase  
Sentence  
A dog  
Animal  A boy  
Person  the playground  
Location  + Entities and relations  CHASE  ON 
Dog(d1 ). Boy(b1). Playground(p1). Chasing(d1,b1,p1 ). + Logic predicates  
Speech Act = REQUEST  + Speech acts  
Deeper NLP: requires more human effort; less accurate  Closer to knowledge  
representation  
Text Representation and Enabled Analysis  
4 Text Rep  Generality   Enabled Analysis  Examples  of Application  
String  String  processing  Compression  
Words  Word relation analysis; topic 
analysis; sentiment analysis  Thesaurus discovery;  topic and 
opinion related applications  
+ Syntactic 
structures  Syntactic  graph analysis  Stylistic  analysis; structure -
based feature extraction  
+ Entities & 
relations  Knowledge  graph analysis; 
information network analysis  Discovery  of knowledge and 
opinions about specific entities  
+ Logic 
predicates   Integrative  analysis of scattered 
knowledge; l ogic inference  Knowledge  assistant for 
biologists  This course  
Summary  
•Text representation determines what kind of mining algorithms can be 
applied  
•Multiple ways of representing text are possible  
–string, words, syntactic structures, entity -relation graphs, 
predicates…  
–can/should be combined  in real applications  
•This course focuses on word -based representation  
–General and robust : applicable to any natural language  
–No/little manual effort  
–“Surprisingly” powerful for many applications (not all!)  
–Can be combined with more sophisticated representations  
 5 
