Word Association Mining and Analysis  
 
ChengXiang  “Cheng” Zhai  
Department of Computer Science  
University of Illinois at Urbana -Champaign  
1 
Word Association Mining & Analysis  
2 Real World  
 Observed World  Text Data  
(English)  Perceive  Express  
(Perspective)  3. Topic mining & analysis  
4. Opinion mining and 
sentiment analysis  5. Text -based prediction  
1.Natural language 
processing  & text 
representation  3. Topic mining and analysis  5. Text -based prediction  
1.Natural language 
processing  and text 
representation  
2. Word association 
mining  and analysis  
Outline  
•What is a word association?  
•Why mine word associations?  
•How to mine word associations?  
3 
Basic Word Relations: Paradigmatic vs. Syntagmatic  
•Paradigmatic:  A & B have paradigmatic relation if they can be 
substituted for each other (i.e., A & B are in the same class)  
–E.g., “cat” and “dog”; “Monday” and “Tuesday”  
•Syntagmatic: A & B have syntagmatic relation if they can be 
combined with each other (i.e., A & B are related semantically)  
–E.g., “cat” and “sit”;  “car” and “drive”  
•These two basic and complementary relations can be generalized 
to describe relations of any items in a language  
4 
Why Mine Word Associations?  
•They are useful for improving accuracy of many NLP tasks  
–POS tagging, parsing, entity recognition, acronym expansion  
–Grammar learning  
•They are directly useful for many applications in text retrieval and 
mining  
–Text retrieval (e.g., use word associations to suggest a variation of a 
query)  
–Automatic construction of topic map for browsing: words as nodes and 
associations as edges  
–Compare and summarize opinions (e.g., what words are most strongly 
associated with “battery” in positive and negative reviews about iPhone 
6, respectively?)  
5 
Mining Word Associations: Intuitions  
6 My  cat eats fish on Saturday  
His  cat  eats turkey on Tuesday  
My dog eats meat on Sunday  
His dog eats turkey on Tuesday  
…   cat:  My  ___ eats  fish on Saturday  
His  ___ eats  turkey on Tuesday  
…  
dog:  My ___  eats  meat on Sunday  
His ___  eats  turkey on Tuesday  
…  Paradigmatic: similar context  
Similar  
left context  Similar  
Right context  Similar  
General context  
How similar are context (“ cat”) and context (“ dog”)? 
How similar are context (“ cat”) and context (“ computer ”)?  
Mining Word Associations: Intuitions  
7 My  cat eats  fish on Saturday  
His  cat  eats  turkey  on Tuesday  
My dog eats  meat  on Sunday  
His dog eats  turkey on Tuesday  
…  Syntagmatic: correlated occurrences  
My  __  eats  __  on Saturday  
His  __  eats  __  on Tuesday  
My __   eats  __  on Sunday  
His __   eats  __  on Tuesday  
…  
What words tend to occur 
to the left of “eats ”? What words  
to the right?  
Whenever “ eats ” occurs, what other words also tend to occur?  
How helpful is the occurrence of “ eats ” for predicting occurrence of “ meat ”? 
How helpful is the occurrence of “eats ” for predicting occurrence of “text”? 
Mining Word Associations: General Ideas  
•Paradigmatic  
–Represent each word by its context  
–Compute context similarity  
–Words with high context similarity likely have paradigmatic relation  
•Syntagmatic   
–Count how many times two words occur together in a context (e.g., 
sentence or paragraph)  
–Compare their co -occurrences with their individual occurrences  
–Words with high co -occurrences but relatively low individual occurrences  
likely have syntagmatic relation     
•Paradigmatically related words tend to have syntagmatic relation with 
the same word   joint discovery of the two relations  
•These ideas can be implemented in many different ways!  
 8 
