Contextual Text Mining: Motivation  
 
ChengXiang “Cheng” Zhai  
Department of Computer Science  
University of Illinois at Urbana -Champaign  
1 
Contextual Text Mining  
2 Real World  
 Observed World  Text Data  
(English)  Perceive  Express  
(Perspective)  3. Topic mining & analysis  
4. Opinion mining and  
    sentiment analysis  5. Text -based prediction  
1.Natural language 
processing  & text 
representation  3. Topic mining and analysis  5. Text -based prediction  
1.Natural language 
processing and text 
representation  
2. Word association 
mining and analysis  
Contextual Text Mining: Motivation  
•Text often has rich context information  
–Direct context (Meta -Data): time, location, authors, source, …  
–Indirect context (additional data related to meta -data): social 
network of the author, author’s age, other text from the same 
source, etc.  
–Any related data can be regarded as context  
•Context can be used to  
–Partition text data for comparative analysis  
–Provide meaning to the discovered topics   
3 
4 
 Context = Partitioning of Text  
1999  
2005  
2006  1998  
…… …… papers written 
in 1998  
WWW  SIGIR  ACL KDD  SIGMOD  papers written by 
authors in the U.S.  Papers about “text mining”  
Enables discovery of knowledge associated with different context as needed  
Many Interesting Questions Require  
Contextual Text Mining  
•What topics have been gaining increasing attention recently in data mining 
research? (time as context)  
•Is there any difference in the responses of people in different regions to the 
event ? (location as context)  
•What are the common research interests of two researchers? (authors as 
context)  
•Is there any difference in the research topics published by authors in the USA 
and those outside? (author’s affiliation and location as context)  
•Is there any difference in the opinions about a topic expressed on one social 
network and another? (social network of authors and topic as context)   
•Are there topics in news data that are correlated with sudden changes in stock 
prices? (time series as context)  
•What issues “mattered” in the 2012 presidential election? (time series as 
context)  5 
